Inventory of the Henry James Brown Papers 1830-1921
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Henry James Brown Papers, 1830-1921.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 65 B845
47 items.
Papers, 1830-1921, consisting of letters and sketches of the Henry James Brown family.
Brown Family,; Henry James Brown,; Mrs. Salina Brown Worsham,; J. S. Worsham.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 46 items, 3/3/1994.
Gift: 1 item, 4/1/1994.
Biographical/Historical Information
Henry James Brown was born 12 October 1811. He studied with George Caleb Bingham and Thomas Sully. He was a portrait painter and a Methodist clergyman and farmer. He married Susan Ann Hobson and died 9 April 1855. His daughter was Salina Brown who married J. S. Worsham.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1830-1921, of the Henry James Brown family. There is a biographical sketch of Henry James Brown an artist, and Methodist clergyman, as well as sketches drawn by him and sermons written by him. The papers also are of other members of his family. Includes a cut-out valentine and a fold-out book of poems illustrated in water color both made by Mary A. Brown, sister of Henry James Brown; cut-out valentines and a bookmark made by Salina Brown Worsham; and correspondence between Salina Brown Worsham and J. S. Worsham, her husband.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Each series in the collection is arranged in chronlogical order.
Organization
This collection is organized into 5 series: 1. Letters, 2. Sermons, 3. Items of or Dealing With Art, 4. Newspaper Clippings, and 5. Genealogical Material - Addition.
Additional Separated Material
Separated Material
Paintings by Henry James Brown, which were presented with the collection, are now part of the Muscarelle Museum, College of William and Mary.
Index Terms
Persons:
Worsham, Salina Brown, Mrs.; Worsham, J. S.
Subjects:
Artists--United States.; Valentines.; Methodist Church--Virginia.; Artists-- Virginia.; Watercolor painting.
Contents List
- James A. Servies, Librarian, to Sydney A. Temple, Curator of Manuscripts, 2 March 1965. (Folder 1)
  Re: papers received.
- Brief sketch of the life of Henry James Brown, written by a granddaughter, Mrs. Christine I. Staton, n.d. (Folder 2)
  Also including a note on Henry James Brown and family. ADr.
  Series 1: Letters
- Letters, personal and business, 1830-1821, n.d., 20 items. (Folder 3-22)
  - Cut-out valentine basket made by Mary Brown, sister of Henry James Brown, [ca. 1830], 1 item. ASk. (Folder 3)
  - Fold-out group of poems illustrated in water color; a children's book made by Mary A. Brown, [ca. 1830], 1 item. AMs, Sk. (Folder 3)
  - Letter - Jennie [ ] to her mother, 7 December 1865. (Folder 4)
    Family affairs.
  - Invitation to Jefferson Society of the University of Virginia, to Salina Brown, Ballsville P.O., Powhatan Co., Virginia, 13 April 1868. (Folder 5)
    S.B. was the daughter of Henry James Brown.
  - Three Cut-out valentines made by Salina Brown, sent to Joe [S] Worsham, her future husband, [ca. 1870], 3 items. ASk. (Folder 6)
  - Bookmark, "With my Love," made by Salina Brown, sent to Joe [S] Worsham, her future husband, [ca. 1870], 1 item. PM. (Folder 6)
  - J.S. Worsham, Cumberland, Mississippi to his "sister," Salina Browne, W. F. College, Murfreesboro, North Carolina, 12 January 1872. (Folder 7)
    Re: Christmas: fireworks nearly every night--young men dressed as Rag muffins--several Christmas trees-- one Christmas present only.
  - Grubbs and Williams, Real Estate Agents, Richmond, to Salina I. Brown, Lynchburg, Virginia, 1873. (Folder 8)
    Re: portion of inheritance from the estate of Henry J. Brown. Enclosure: an account sheet.
  - J. S. Worsham, Mississippi, to Salina Browne, Lycnhburg, Virginia, 1 April 1877. (Folder 9)
    Compares the Mississippi River with the James River; comments unfavorably on the Mardi Gras celebration in Memphis.
  - J. S. Worsham, Mississippi, to his "sister," Salina Browne, Farmville, Virginia, 12 January 1878. (Folder 10)
    Re: snow and a sleigh ride.
  - J. S. Worsham, Michigan City, Mississippi, to his "sister," Salina Browne, Farmville, Virginia, 8 March 1878., 8 pages. ALS, C. (Folder 11)
    Re: Trip back from Virginia; married a couple on his way; unpleasant visit to a poorhouse; visits with Salina's sister, Mrs. Winfree, and other members of the family; the proposal that he has made to her.
  - J. S. Worsham, Michigan City, Mississippi, to Salina Browne, Farmville, Virginia, 13 May 1878., 6 pages. ALS, C. (Folder 12)
    Re: his activities in raising cattle.
  - J. S. Worsham, Michigan City, Mississippi, to Salina Browne, Farmville, Virginia, 1 June 1878. (Folder 13)
    Sent with a box he has made on occasion of her commencement; news of Jennie; the temperance movement "is all the rage."
  - J. S. Worsham, Michigan City, Mississippi, to Salina Browne, care Mr. C. V. Winfree, Lynchburg, Virginia, 12 June 1878. (Folder 14)
    Brief letter.
  - J. S. Worsham, Michigan City, Mississippi, to Salina Browne, Clinton, Powhatan Co., Virginia, 10 July 1878., 6 pages. ALS, C. (Folder 15)
    Re: his planned visit to Virginia.
  - J. S. Worsham, Michigan City, Mississippi, to Salina Browne, "Sunnyside," Cumberland, Virginia, 18 August 1878. (Folder 16)
    Re: Yellow Fever which is causing some towns to be deserted and some of the railroads to stop running-- many refugees from Memphis.
  - J. S. Worsham, Knoxville, Tennesse, to Salina Browne, Lynchburg, Virginia, 27 October 1878. (Folder 17)
    Re: the engagement of S.B.; enclosure a photo.
  - J. S. Worsham, Knoxville, Tennesse, to Salina Browne, Lynchburg, Virginia, 29 October 1878. (Folder 18)
    On his way home.
  - Edward [ ], Lynchburg, to his niece, Salina, 23 August 1880. (Folder 19)
    Re: inherited property, family news; "Love to Joe and a kiss to your little baby."
  - [Salina Brown Worsham], Lynchburg, to her husband, J.S. Worsham, Michigan City, Benton County, Mississippi, 5 August 1881. (Folder 20)
    Ill in bed, she writes of family affairs-- of her longing for her husband but her hate of Mississippi.
  - A letter about a Bible Class in Lynchburg with pencil notes added, 21 October 1921. (Folder 21)
  - P.A. Brown to his sister, 7 October [ ]29. (Folder 22)
    Re: his failing health; family affairs.
- Unsigned poem, n.d., 2 pages. AMs. (Folder 23)
  First line: "How transient the things of this life."
  Series 2: Sermons
- Sermons, n.d., 4 items. (Folder 24-27)
  - Sermon on the test Jer. viii.22, n.d., 16 pages. AMsS. (Folder 24)
    Endorsed, Rev. Henry J. Brown and Susan S. Brown, Powhatan County, Virginia.
  - Sermon [by Henry James Brown], titled, "Predestination Condemned," n.d., 19 pages. AMs. (Folder 25)
  - Sermon [by Henry James Brown], n.d., 22 pages. AMs. Incomplete. (Folder 26)
  - Sermon [by Henry James Brown], text from 1st Chronicles, n.d. (Folder 27)
  Series 3: Items of or dealing with art
- Items of or dealing with art, 1859, n.d., 11 items. (Folder 28-30)
  - Notes on preparing paper for photographic drawing, etc., [1859]. (Folder 28)
    Endorsed: "This paper was written by my father Henry J. Brown in 1839...June 16, 1923...Salina J. Worsham."
  - Paintings and sketches by Henry James Brown, n.d., 8 items. (Folder 29)
    - Color miniature of a couple, n.d., 4" x 4.5". (Folder 29)
    - Color sketch of children playing, indoor scene, n.d., 6" x 7.5". (Folder 29)
    - Pencil sketches of sculptured heads of Franklin and Washington, n.d., ?" x 9". (Folder 29)
    - Comic pencil sketch of man's head (perhaps self-portrait), n.d., 7.5" x 9". (Folder 29)
    - Pencil Sketch of a child's head, n.d., 8" x 10.5". (Folder 29)
    - Pencil sketch of a woman's head, 8.5" x 12". (Folder 29)
    - Pencil sketch of a girl's head, n.d., 8" x 12.5". (Folder 29)
    - Oil painting on canvas of man's bust, 8" x 10". (Folder 29)
  - Miniature painting in oil on cardboard by S[alina] B[rown] Worsham, n.d., 8.5" x 6". (Folder 30)
    It probably represents a local scene in Lynchburg, Virginia, toward the end of the 19th century.
  - Ink wash sketch entitled "Somerset, Home of Henry James Brown." Unsigned, n.d., 8" x 10". (Folder 30)
  Series 4: Newspaper Clippings
- Newspaper Clippings, 1873-1941, 2 items. (Folder 31-32)
  - Obituary notice of Susan A. Brown, widow of Henry J. Brown, of Powhatan County, Virginia, 11 May 1873. (Folder 31)
  - Article in the [ ] News, Lynchburg, Virginia, on exhibition of portraits by Henry James Brown, 16 October 1941. (Folder 32)
- Cut out advertisement of "Superior Bisquits," n.d., PM. (Folder 33)
- Photographs of paintings owned by the Muscarelle Museum, n.d., 4 items. Ph. (Folder 34)
  Photographs of the Henry James Brown paintings.
  Series 5: Genealogical Material - Addition
- Genealogical Material - Addition 1985, (revised 1989)., 5 folders. XCy. (Othertype 1994.20.)
  Addition to the Henry James Brown Papers. Photocopied book entitled "The Brownes/Browns of London, Virginia, and Missouri," (which includes a sketch of Henry James Brown, artist of Virginia) by Charles Walker Whitman, 1985 (revised 1989).